- 嘿，雷
- 把门关上。关上！
- Hey, Ray.
- Shut the door. Shut it!
- 为什么，为什么？
- 关上门，别乱动！
- Why why?
- Shut the door and don't waIk anywhere!
- 别动！
- 你吓着我了，兄弟！
- Don't move!
- You're freakin' me out, man!
- 到底怎么了？
- 我得――我弄丢了仓鼠，
- What's going on?
- I've gotta-- I Iost the hamster,
爱丽的仓鼠
AIIy's hamster.
- 哦，不，它跑出来了？
- 是的，他跑出来了。见了鬼了
- Oh, no, he got out?
- Yes, he got out. What the heII?
快点。黛比拉和孩子们
再过一小时就回来了
Come on. Debra and the kids are
gonna be home in an hour.
你得帮我找找
You gotta heIp me
Iook for him.
他们把你一个人丢在家
一个周末，
They Ieave you aIone
for one weekend,
这房子里唯一一个其他的活物就得逃走
and the onIy other Iiving thing
in the house needs to run away.
妈，你在干嘛？
你不帮帮我吗？
Ma, you're supposed
to heIp me.
你看看这些面包渣子
WouId you Iook
at these crumbs?
黛比拉就这么收拾厨房，
The way Debra
keeps this kitchen,
这屋子里没闹仓鼠灾
已经是奇迹了
it's a miracIe this pIace isn't
infested with hamsters.
不在地下室里
He's not in the basement.
爸，我先说清楚，
我们要活的
Dad, just so you know, we want
the hamster brought back aIive.
这得看它了
That's up to him.
好了，我检查完了整个顶层
AII right, I checked out
the entire top fIoor
没看到粗面包的影子
and no sign
of PumpernickeI.
顺便说一句，
抽屉上层不是藏值钱东西的好地方
By the way, you shouIdn't hide
vaIuabIes in your top drawer.
并且你该买身新内衣了
And you couId use some
new underwear, Raymond.
我会记在购物单上的，亲爱的
I'II put it on the Iist, dear.
再过一小时他们就回来了
They're gonna
be back in an hour.
我去买个新仓鼠
I'm gonna go
get a new hamster.
- 你不能这样
- 为什么不？
- You can't do that.
- Why not?
它们看起来都一样。
他不会看出来的
They aII Iook aIike.
She'II never know the difference.
你打算这么骗你女儿？
You wouId Iie
to your daughter Iike that?
我不会骗她的。
我只会这么说：
I'm not gonna Iie.
I'm just gonna say,
“你的仓鼠，亲爱的。”
''Here's your hamster, honey.''
我要告诉爱丽
I'm teIIing AIIy.
- 你管好自己的事吧
- 你找不到一样的
- You just mind your business.
- You're not gonna find one
哦，是的
- that Iooks the same.
- Oh, yeah.
我上哪去找一只棕色的仓鼠啊？
Where am I gonna find
a brown hamster?
我不能合伙这么撒谎
I cannot be a party
to that Iie.
你闭嘴就好了，条子
You just keep your
mouth shut, Copper.
别叫我闭嘴
Don't teII me to shut up.
- 我来让你闭上怎么样？
- 我就在这等着你！
- How about I make you?
- How about I'm right over here?
- 我上你那去怎么样？
- 放马过来呀！
- How about I come over there?
- Bring it on!
- 我全放
- 停下！
- I'II bring everything on.
- Stop it!
乖，孩子们
Be nice, boys.
好了。
咱们都需要喘口气
AII right now.
We aII need a break.
先吃点小零食，
Let's have a snack,
然后说不定粗面包
听到咱们吃东西，
and maybe if PumpernickeI
hears us enjoying our food,
它就会过来了
he'II join us.
它可以分点你的。
别想跟我抢
He can have some of yours.
He's not getting any of mine.
- 爸
- 怎么了？
- Dad.
- What?
我正要办这个呢。
你起来好吗？
I'm trying to move it.
CouId you get up?
捎我一段
Give me a ride.
怎么了，妈，怎么了？
What is it, Ma, what?
哦，老兄，它在这
Oh boy, there he is.
- 哪？
- 就在那
- Where?
- Right there.
什么？我只看到雪糕
What? AII I see
is fudge pops.
看看左边长毛的那个
Look at the hairy one
on the Ieft.
什么？
What?
我靠
HoIy crap.
你做了什么？
What did you do?
我做了什么？
什么，你以为我把它放进去的？
What did I do?
What, you think I put him in?
我不知道它怎么进去的
I don't know how
he got in there.
哦，它自己爬进密封的冰箱的？
Oh, he cIimbed into
an airtight freezer by himseIf?
我不知道这到底怎么发生的
I don't know how this
couId have happened.
我打扫完仓鼠笼子，
I cIeaned out
the hamster cage,
我准是没把笼子合严实
and I must not have snapped
the cage back together tight enough.
等等，等一等。
然后我去了食品店
Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
Then I went grocery shopping.
你把食品袋放桌上了？
Did you have
the groceries on the tabIe?
它一定是爬进袋子里了
He must have cIimbed
into the bag
有雪糕的那个
that had the fudge pops.
看哪，看看它的小胡子。
全是雪糕
Look, Iook at his whiskers.
They're aII fudgy.
呃唔！
Ew!
它的最后一顿饭
His Iast meaI.
可怜的粗面包
Poor PumpernickeI.
爱丽一定会恨我的
AIIy's gonna hate me.
- 嘿，给我一根
- 别添乱？
- Hey, give me one of those.
- WiII you get out of here?
喔喔，等等，等一下
Whoa whoa, wait a minute.
Wait a minute.
- 也许它还没死
- 什么，你讲笑话呢？
- He may not be dead.
- What, are you kidding?
你都能拿那个砸胡桃了
You couId crack a waInut
with that thing.
不，我是认真的。
它也许只是冷冻保存了
No, I'm serious. He may be
cryogenicaIIy preserved
暂时失去生命迹象而已
in a state of
suspended animation.
它死了，好吗？
我得去买只新的
He's dead, aII right?
I have to buy another one now.
好吧，看，不一定的，雷
Okay, Iook,
not necessariIy, Ray.
也许咱们能让它苏醒
We may be abIe
to resuscitate him.
嘿，放微波炉里热热
Hey, Iet's toss him
in the microwave.
好了，够了。
我来指挥行动
AII right, that's it.
I'm taking over this operation.
妈，去拿几条毛巾。
爸，我需要点冰。雷蒙德，冷却器
Ma, get me some toweIs.
Dad, I need some ice. Raymond, a cooIer.
咱们送粗面包见兽医
We're evacuating
PumpernickeI to the vet.
咱们走。走走走走
Let's go. Move move
move move move.
罗伯特，兽医也不能让仓鼠
起死回生
Robert, the vet is not gonna
revive a hamster, okay?
这不过是可替换的宠物
These are disposabIe pets.
那你女儿的感受呢，雷？
那也是可替换的吗？
What about your daughter's feeIings,
Ray? Are those disposabIe?
- 好吧
- 不，这不好
- AII right.
- No, it's not aII right!
我碰巧关心一个小女孩。
等她知道她爸爸
I happen to care about a IittIe girI
whose heart is gonna break
在可以的时候
没有尽力救她心爱的仓鼠，
if she finds out that her daddy
didn't do everything he couId
她一定伤心死了
to save the Iife
of her precious hamster.
该死的，雷蒙德，把冷却器拿来
Now damn it, Raymond,
get me that cooIer.
嘿，雷，你忘了做冰块了
Hey, Ray, you forgot
to fiII the ice trays.
直接和雪糕放一块好了
WeII, then we'II just
pack him with fudge pops.
- 这些冻鱼片怎么样？
- 也一块放进来
- What about this box of fish sticks?
- Throw them in too.
等黛比拉回来，
我会教她怎么做真的鱼
When Debra comes home,
I'II show her how to cook a reaI fish.
黛比拉
Debra.
弗兰克
Frank.
起来
Get up.
- 哈？
- 快点，这地方真是一团糟
- Huh?
- Come on, this pIace is a mess.
你什么都没干
You haven't done a thing.
嘿，别打搅我。
我要歇会
Hey, Ieave me aIone.
I'm taking a break.
你干什么了？
What have you been doing?
我把厨房整顿好了，
I not onIy straightened
out the kitchen,
台子擦干净了，
冰箱也收拾完了
I scrubbed the countertops,
and I cIeaned out the freezer.
然后你就开私酒庆祝了？
And you ceIebrate
with a bottIe of hooch?
哦
Oh.
- 嘿，我们回来了
- 嗨，奶奶。嗨，爷爷
- Hey, we're home.
- Hi, Grandma. Hi, Grandpa.
- 嘿，甜心
- 弗兰克
- Hey, sweetheart.
- Frank.
嗨，甜心。
这不是我的
Hi, sweetheart.
This isn't mine.
这是妈咪的
This is Mommy's.
- 玛丽，雷呢？
-雷蒙德得出去一趟，
- Marie, where's Ray?
- Raymond had to rush out,
不过他很快就会回来了
but he shouId
be back soon.
为什么我的客厅
像是兄弟会分坛
Why does my Iiving room
Iook Iike a frat house?
我没看出来有什么不一样
I didn't notice
any difference reaIIy.
- 嗨，爸爸！
- 哦，嘿嘿
- Hi, Daddy!
- Oh, hey hey.
嘿，小家伙们，你们回来了。嗨
Everybody, you're home. Hi.
嘿。嗨，玩得开心吗？
哦天，想死你了
Hey. Hi, how was your visit?
Oh boy, I missed you.
你爸呢？他的膝盖……
怎么，他的膝盖……
How's your father? He's got a knee--
What, he have a knee--
- 哦，他买了辆新车
- 雷。雷……
- oh, he got a new car.
- Ray. Ray...
这里是怎么了？
What happened here?
- 哦，没什么。怎么了？
- 这是什么？
- Oh, nothing. Why?
- What's that?
哦，哦，我们带粗面包兜风去了
Oh, oh, we gave
PumpernickeI a ride
坐罗伯特的警车
in Robert's poIice car.
是的是的。
它也喜欢这个
Yeah yeah.
He Iiked it, too.
一路都把脑袋伸出窗外
Rode the whoIe way
with his head out the window.
这不是粗面包
This isn't PumpernickeI.
爸爸，粗面包哪去了？
Daddy, where's PumpernickeI?
呃蕖…
Um...
um--
粗面包和冻鱼片睡一块了
PumpernickeI sIeeps
with the fish sticks.
你知道，爱丽，
据我看来
You know, AIIy,
it's my understanding
冷冻几乎是安乐死了
that freezing is a virtuaIIy
painIess way to go.
- 不像婚姻，那种痛苦……
- 弗兰克！
- UnIike marriage, where the pain is--
- Frank!
我能看看粗面包吗？
Can I see PumpernickeI?
- 爱丽，你不能
- 当然可以，亲爱的
- AIIy, you shouIdn't.
- Sure, honey.
- 你可以过去看看它
- 什么？
- You can go see him.
- What?
- 这对心理闭合很重要
It's important for cIosure.
心理闭合
CIosure.
又看书了？
Reading books again?
为什么它身上全是冰淇淋？
Why is he covered
in chocoIate?
一定是雪糕化了
Some of the fudge pops
must have meIted.
- 雪糕？
- 我要！我要！
- Fudge pops?
- Gimme! Gimme!
- 不不，别过去！
- 不，孩子们，停下
- No no, get out of there!
- No, guys, stop that.
- 那不是雪糕
- 厨房里有饼干
- That's not fudge.
- There's cookies in the kitchen.
- 去去去快去
- 到这来，亲爱的
- Go go go go go go.
- Come here, sweetheart.
重要的是，爱丽
The important thing
to know, AIIy,
粗面包进天堂了
is that PumpernickeI
is in heaven.
- 不是真的
- 弗兰克
- Not reaIIy.
- Frank.
不是真的天堂，
不是人的天堂
Not reaI heaven,
not peopIe heaven.
- 只有一个天堂
- 告诉你点信息吧，
- There's onIy one heaven.
- For your information,
动物有单独的天堂
there's a whoIe separate
heaven for animaIs.
- 你上哪知道的？
- 圣经上写的
- And just where did you Iearn that?
- It's in the BibIe.
- 好想你看过圣经似的
- 我看过各种该死的圣经
- Like you read the BibIe.
- I've read pIenty of damn BibIes.
所有的动物都能进天堂吗，
还是只有宠物？
Do aII animaIs go
to heaven or just pets?
所有的动物都跟咱们上人的天堂
AII animaIs go
to peopIe heaven with us, dear.
人的天堂是人的
PeopIe heaven's
for peopIe.
你奶奶喝醉了
Your grandma's
been hitting the sauce.
好吧
AII right.
谢谢。
谢谢你的正解
Thank you.
Thanks for cIearing that up.
动物是不是也有下地狱的？
Do some animaIs
go to heII?
我们不用这样的字眼，爱丽
We don't use
those words, AIIy.
坏动物下地狱，孩子
Bad animaIs
go to heII, kid.
相信我，我知道
BeIieve you me,
I know.
我在你这年纪，
When I was your age,
有一个叫艾尔沙的恶毒的德国牧羊人
there was this mean
oId German shepherd named EIsa.
有一天我走路上学
I was waIking
to schooI one day
我准是经过的时候
太靠近她的领地了
and I must have crossed
too cIose to her territory.
那年头，德国人
对领地很敏感
In those days, the Germans were
very sensitive about their territory.
这理由就足够
WeII, that's aII it took
让纳粹母狼艾尔沙寡妇
for FrauIein EIsa
the Nazi she-woIf
跳将出来，
从我的纯美国皮下
to jump out
and take a hunk out
咬下一大块肉
of my aII-American hide.
伤疤现在还在
I stiII have the scar.
- 想看看吗？我让你们看看
- 不，弗兰克
- You want to see it? I'II show you.
- No, Frank!
你干什么？
坐下
What are you doing?
Sit down.
好吧！
AII right!
我想说的是，艾尔沙寡妇
这会很可能就在地狱
The point is FrauIein EIsa's probabIy
in heII right now
拖着她的纳粹屁股
从魔鬼的地毯上过
dragging her Nazi butt
across the deviI's carpet.
谢谢这么感人的故事
Thank you for that
heartwarming story.
看，爱丽，我很抱歉
发生这种事，
Look, AIIy, I'm very sorry
that this happened,
现在来见见你的全新的仓鼠
but now it's time to meet
your brand-new hamster.
- 不，谢谢
- 哦，别这样，看，看哪
- No, thanks.
- Oh, come on, Iook Iook.
它看起来和原来的粗面包
没两样
He Iooks just Iike
the oId PumpernickeI.
宠物店的人说，
And the guy at
the store toId me
再过几年，
没准它能飞起来
that in a coupIe years,
he might fIy.
雷！
Ray!
雷，别跟她那么说
Ray, don't teII her that.
好吧
AII right.
好吧，它不会……
它不会飞
AII right, so he won't--
he's not gonna fIy.
不过他真的说了
它有魔力
But he did say
that he's magicaI.
- 雷
- 它的个性！
- Ray.
- His personaIity!
- 不，爸爸
- 哦，别这样，爱丽
- No, Dad.
- Oh, come on, AIIy.
看看它。
它是个可爱的小替代
Just take a Iook.
He's a cute IittIe repIacement.
我不想要替代，爸爸
I don't want
a repIacement, Daddy.
我想这正是她需要的――
一个替代的父亲
I think that's exactIy what she needs--
a repIacement daddy.
你能回去吗，求你了？
CouId you go home, pIease?
把这两个神学家一并带走
And take these two
theoIogians with you.
你不理解，亲爱的
You don't understand,
sweetie.
一个孩子的宠物死的时候，
When a chiId's pet dies,
在能够接受别的宠物之前，
she has to go through
a grieving process
她必定会经历哀悼的过程
before she can
take on a new pet.
好了，你能看书。
我们知道了
AII right, you can read.
We get it.
为这种事大做文章
是不是有病啊？
Isn't it a IittIe morbid
to make such a big deaI out of this?
不，这不是有病。
这是现实
No, it's not morbid.
It's reaIity.
哦，得了吧。
就是只仓鼠
Oh, come on.
It's a hamster.
由她去吧，
她会好的
Just Ieave her aIone,
and she'II get over it.
你知道怎样对所有孩子
的健康都有好处？
You know what I think
wouId be heaIthy for aII the kids?
如果咱们能为粗面包举行
正式的告别仪式
If we have sort of a formaI
goodbye ceremony for PumpernickeI.
- 好主意，黛比
- 雷可以在后院挖个洞
- Good idea, Deb.
- Ray can dig a hoIe in the backyard.
- 我才不挖洞
- 你要挖的
- I'm not digging a hoIe.
- You're digging a hoIe.
- 我去拿个鞋盒
- 好，我去摆点奶酪、冷荤
- I wiII get a shoebox.
- Okay, I'II put out the coId cuts.
好的
Okay.
我去拿啤酒
I'II get some beer.
好了，咱们来举行葬礼
AII right,
Iet's put on a funeraI.
嘿
Hey.
怎么样了？
How's it going?
我在暴风雨里挖石头
I'm digging through soIid
rock in a rainstorm.
你想会怎么样？
How do you think
it's going?
你是什么，糖做的？
叫毛毛雨都勉强
What are you, made of sugar?
It's bareIy drizzIing.
啊！
Ah!
小心点，亲爱的
CarefuI, honey.
你怎么不来挖？
再怎么说这都是你的错
Why don't you dig this hoIe?
This is aII your fauIt anyway.
你该告诉我笼子坏了一块的
You shouId have toId me about
that broken piece on the hamster cage.
嘿，你要是稍微用点心，
Hey, if you were
a IittIe more invoIved,
你就会注意到这些细节的
you'd pick up
on these detaiIs.
- 哦，是吗？
- 是的
- Oh, reaIIy?
- Yeah.
也许我该把坑挖大点
Maybe I make this hoIe
a IittIe bigger.
哦，拜托，爸
Oh, come on, Dad.
又是这个金属探测器？
你干什么呢？
Again with the metaI detector?
What are you doing?
你妈就要过生日了
Your mother's
birthday's coming up.
聪明，这除了你爸就是石头
Yeah, weII, there's nothing
here but dirt and rocks.
这比他去年送我的好多了
That's better than what
he got me Iast year.
好了，爱丽，咱们把盒子放进去，
然后给它盖上土
AII right, AIIy, we'II put the box in,
and then I'II put the dirt on him.
等等，我想每个人先对
粗面包说段话
Wait. I want everybody to say
something about PumpernickeI first.
哦，好极了，好的
Oh, that's good, yeah.
然后咱们都给它撒上一把土
Then we'II aII take
a handfuI of dirt and toss it in.
- 你干什么？
- 这是她的愿望
- What are you doing?
- That's what she wants.
在下雨呢，亲爱的
It's raining, honey.
我想咱们应该按爱丽的方式做。
你想上我伞下来吗？
I think we shouId do this AIIy's way.
You wanna get under my umbreIIa?
我在我现在的地方很好，
非常感谢
I'm wonderfuI right where
I am, thank you very much.
爸爸，你想开始吗？
Daddy, wouId you
Iike to start?
哦，我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
亲爱的，为什么不让爷爷先来呢？
说吧
Honey, why don't we Iet
Grandpa start? Go ahead.
爷爷
Grandpa.
爸，你先别探了好吗？
Dad, couId you power
down for a second?
哈？
Huh?
噢噢噢噢
Oh oh oh oh.
好的好的。
呃……
AII right, aII right.
Uh...
粗面包
PumpernickeI--
就像仓鼠，喜欢面包
Iiked the hamster,
Iove the bread.
下一个
Next.
奶奶
Grandma.
好的，亲爱的
Okay, dear.
虽然粗面包离开了人世间，
Even though PumpernickeI
has gone from this earth,
我知道它会永远从天堂看着咱们
I know he'II aIways
be Iooking down at us from heaven.
人的天堂
PeopIe heaven.
好了，继续，罗伯特叔叔
AII right, go ahead,
UncIe Robert.
死亡……
Death--
最后的再见
the finaI goodbye.
终极的道别
The uItimate toodIe-oo.
或许，死亡不是尽头
Or maybe death
is not the end.
也许它是个起点
Maybe it's a beginning.
也许，它是终极的问好
Perhaps, it's
the uItimate howdy-do.
你搞笑呢？
你搞笑吧？
Are you kidding me?
怎么了，雷？
对你太深刻了？
What's the matter, Ray,
too deep for you?
哦，天
Oh, God.
继续，罗伯特
Go ahead, Robert.
你知道，我想明白了，
You know, I have come
to the concIusion that
我死的时候，我愿意像
粗面包那样死去
when I die, I wouId Iike
to die Iike PumpernickeI,
平静、没有痛苦，
quietIy, painIessIy,
嘴角还沾着巧克力雪糕
chocoIate fudge pop stuck
to the corner of my mouth.
因为那样，我的朋友，
一定是个幸福的死法
For that, my friends,
must be a happy death.
Aloha（夏威夷语）
AIoha,
意思是再见和你好
which means goodbye
and heIIo.
- 好吧
- Shalom（希伯来语）也是一样的意思
- AII right.
- Same with shaIom.
- 闭嘴。只许说一个意思的
- 好了，雷
- Shut up. One meaning.
- AII right, Ray.
该你了，妈咪
Your turn, Mommy.
好的，
Okay, weII,
我一直感觉和粗面包很亲近，
I've aIways feIt
very cIose to PumpernickeI,
特别是，
我喂它吃的，打扫洗澡
especiaIIy since I did
a Iot of the feeding and cIeaning
你知道，大部分的活
and, you know,
most of the work.
所以粗面包的离去
会在我生活里留下一个大空洞
So PumpernickeI's passing
is gonna Ieave a big hoIe in my Iife.
我都不知道怎么打发那些时间了
Can't imagine what
I'II do with the time.
再见，粗面包
So Iong, PumpernickeI.
- 麦克
- 爱丽，为什么
- MichaeI.
- AIIy, why don't we do
不把双胞胎当背景人物呢？
the twins as a set, okay?
- 雷――雷，上我伞下面来
- 在下雨
- Ray-- Ray, come under my umbreIIa.
- 'Cause it's raining.
嘿，别说话――
仓鼠葬礼
Hey, no taIking--
hamster funeraI.
我回想你的，粗面包
I'II miss you,
PumpernickeI.
- 杰弗里
- 我也会想你的，粗面包
- Jeffrey.
- I'II miss you too, PumpernickeI.
轮我了
Now my turn.
我也回想你的，粗面包
I'II miss you too,
PumpernickeI.
你曾是我最好的朋友，
现在也是
You were my best friend,
and you stiII are.
别担心，粗面包
Don't worry, PumpernickeI.
你会永远和我在一起，
因为我永远不会忘记你的
You'II aIways be with me,
'cause I'II never forget you.
该你了，爸爸
Your turn, Daddy.
呃……
Uh...
嗯……
um...
我没有太多的接触……|
I didn't have much
contact with--
我不是太认识粗面包
I didn't know
PumpernickeI very weII.
我记得唯一一件事是
The onIy thing
I remember is
我们把它从宠物店带回来的时候，
when we brought him back
from the pet store,
爱丽想让我抱抱它，
and AIIy wanted me
to hoId him,
所以我一把抓住它
so I reached out
to grab him
然后它咬了我手指头
and he bit me
on the finger.
很疼
And it hurt.
然后爸爸说了不好的话
So Daddy said
a bad word.
可是爱丽拿起……
But AIIy picked up the--
粗面包
然后教我……
PumpernickeI
and she showed me--
叫我怎么抱它
showed me how
to hoId him.
像这样
Like this.
对吗？
Right?
我从没注意到你长那么大了，
I never noticed
untiI just now
直到刚才
how grown-up you are.
你和你朋友在一起的样子，
The way you were
with your friend,
你刚刚说的话
and what you said
just now,
你真的……
you reaIIy--
真的看来长大了
reaIIy seem grown-up.
我真为你骄傲
I'm proud of you.
该死的仓鼠！
Damn hamster!
爸爸？
Daddy?
明天能给我们买兔子吗？
Can we get
a rabbit tomorrow?
似的，孩子们，
随便你们想要什么
Yeah, guys,
whatever you want.
- 耶！
- 酷！兔子！呜！
- Yeah!
- CooI! A rabbit! Whoo!
呀呼！耶！
Yahoo! Yeah!
兔子。
坑还要大
Rabbit.
That's a bigger hoIe.
你们都笑我，哈？
You aII Iaughed at me, huh?
浪费时间，哈？
Big waste of time, huh?
哈？！
Huh?!
我这就给自己买罐Yoo-hoo
I think I'II buy
myseIf a Yoo-hoo.
我的生日礼物就这么完了
There goes
my birthday present.
jojoba
yettoreturn@hotmail.com